we're doing class 9 okay ACI course one
class nine and that we reach the third
principle path which is yeah correct
view of reality where where is correct
view in the kitchen by the way I say
okay this is my big thing now this geshe
michael says every single idea in the
300,000 books of buddhism is in the
kitchen
and if you're a really good ACI teacher
you can find every hai idea in Buddhism
is in the kitchen when you're fighting
with your husband okay
alright I say the whole thing is there
then I had another understanding like a
few days later on a tour if it's not in
the kitchen
Buddha wouldn't put it in the scripture
okay got it
okay so where is what did I ask where is
the third principle path in the kitchen
not bad yeah the wife view has to be a
state of mind right so the wife is
looking at the husband and the wife is
understanding he's not the one that I
didn't do anything husband right I wish
we had mr. guy Ayrton in Mexico he does
it so well
I can't waiting I think he must do it is
wife sometimes
party his he doesn't so well and the I
didn't do anything husband doesn't exist
that's all and that's correct view okay
don't make it more complicated than that
if you want to help people as an ACI
teacher bring it to the kitchen okay if
you really want to help people give them
something they can take home and not not
philosophy okay so keep talking about
the kitchen okay I got the copyright to
the two husbands in the kitchen I say
you can use it okay but not the week
before I teach it in her country then
always bring it to the kitchen okay
bring emptiness in the kitchen otherwise
I think Nancy can tell you we grew up in
the same time we were both hippies
hundred years ago and I think we didn't
really understand the kitchen for twenty
years you know nobody taught it to us
clearly you know we got we studied we
studied with many many llamas and we
attended many classes and we couldn't
tell you what's happening in the kitchen
you see so please don't do that okay
don't teach emptiness without the
kitchen okay and then everything else is
easy okay but I had a heart sutra geshe
michael has the two husbands in the
kitchen
mine's better we're probably going to
recite it at weddings in the future
once I was to us with the nicotine and
welcome home I get 20 it's better when
your kids get married okay huh yeah
we'll try it and Bobbie but I'll tell
you something people like things they
don't understand
so maybe we do it in French or something
all right
okay here's the first question let's do
the whole hormone homework in the
kitchen okay let's check to do the
homework in the kitchen and I'm gonna
finish this homework tonight I don't
care how long it takes but because I'm
grandpa I think it might magically end
around 9 o'clock there are two realities
in the kitchen there's two levels to
reality okay there's two kinds of
reality first give me the name ultimate
reality and deceptive reality
now the word deceptive is difficult in
English it almost doesn't pass the
waiter test you can say there's a
reality which does not lie to you and
there's a reality which does lie to you
okay there's a reality which always
speaks true to you and there's a reality
but you're always in lies to you okay
let's go from there okay so one of your
biggest jobs as a ACI teacher is to
avoid the big words of Buddhism in the
past okay don't I remember I went into
the first class you're going to
something from samsara my during the
pendant origination in the suchness of
the football and then all of you in your
monk lashes will be
completely Shante Vipassana and I'm like
I said I understood the DA and the a huh
so come on you know your teacher you're
not like I don't know you didn't help
anybody okay so start your emptiness
with the kitchen okay and go from there
then you can start adding ideas okay so
someone where's the where's the reality
in the kitchen which is lying to you
yeah it looks like the husband is
yelling and you didn't do anything
it looks like done okay it looks like
that sometimes you travel on this
Highway in the desert you'll see a big
lake you know 200 miles away and it's
illusion
so all these Buddhist people especially
these Russians Ukrainians who love
Russian speakers they are very misty
Chesky they love mystery so they will
say Oh life is like a Yujin how do you
say illusion Podolski illusion then try
to explain it okay don't just do this
misty Chesky explain it okay this is
illusion
what's illusion in the kitchen what's
the illusion in the kitchen yeah it
looks like he yelled at you and you
didn't do anything but actually you did
do something and if you think you didn't
do anything that's an illusion okay
that's an illusion and there listen
there's no other illusion in Buddhism
okay I trust me John got the books I
studied them there's nothing else there
okay there's nothing else there if you
understand the kitchen well you
understand any school any book any topic
okay it's enough I'm kind of it's kind
of disappointing to spend 25 years in
the Getty course
and somebody could have just told me
about the kitchen you know so anyway
yeah that's deceptive reality reality
which is lying to you okay
and all of the reality you ever
experienced in your life so far was
deceptive reality 100% 100% okay
what's pramana mean correct perception
accurate perception in the highest
school of Buddhism there's no permanent
no such thing it's always lying to you
yeah you're always wrong okay it's kind
of weird okay there's no real symbol
you're never right it's like living with
a woman you're you're never right okay
get used to it now you have two
destructive realities in your life okay
I make jokes like that nowadays people
say you shouldn't make jokes like that I
don't know I have fun with it if
Veronica's here I promise I will say it
maybe I will hear a lecture later okay
what's the opposite of deceptive reality
yeah ultimate reality now normal human
being
never sees it in their lifetime maybe
once when two times during the death
process briefly for a few seconds it's
like it's like a car going by and you're
like and most people never realize what
it is but emptiness appears to you
during death also if you're very deep
into an orgasm okay you will have a
minute some kind of you will touch
emptiness very slightly okay and I think
that's maybe why sex is so addicting
we're going to talk about it tomorrow
but maybe that's why that experience
is so powerful death is also addicting
just kidding okay all right anyway
ultimate reality in that DCI level seven
we talk about touching ultimate reality
we call it the diamond world because we
want the courses to be available to
people in all countries and all
religions so we call it diamond world we
don't call it emptiness and I'd like to
compare it to Manhattan so I worked in
Manhattan for 19 years
it's an island the train station grand
central train station I think a
millionaire to have people walk across
that floor every day and the reason they
can put tall buildings in Manhattan
especially southern Manhattan is that it
has a bedrock foundation so it's a weird
Island it's not dirt it's pure wrong in
fact they found a a nine foot garnet
underneath when they built the subways
it's one of the largest crystals in the
world so it's pure rock you see but when
you walk across this busy train station
how many people from the
million-and-a-half people think about
the rock three feet under nobody okay
they are not aware of it okay it's it's
it's right there every morning every
night when they go home they run across
don't get in the way of one of these
people they'd have a tie on
they have expensive suit and if you are
eating a pretzel or something they will
smash into you right Steven
they'll just smash into you don't get in
their way they're trying to get home
okay but none of those people think
about what's underneath you see and
concourse a emptiness is very similar
okay it's around you all the time
it's around us all the time every object
in this room okay the light the ceiling
the booger again I forgot to wipe off
his nose P ball is giving me booger
advice
everything has emptiness all there all
things have emptiness okay but we can't
see it and we don't think about it okay
so that's ultimate reality if you can
touch it for twenty minutes you will
become a Buddha within a few short time
okay I like to call it like a cancer
starts on the inside a good cancer and
you start to become living timer the
inside becomes living time in like one
small piece and then it starts to spread
in the body in you know I don't know if
there's such a thing but if some person
who saw emptiness decide they don't want
to become Buddha it's too late okay like
I can't imagine but if you see emptiness
directly and you say you know I'm not
really into the Buddha thing you can't
stop it it's like trying to stop it's
already metastasized as soon as you see
the emptiness you cannot stop it okay
you're already becoming a Buddha from
the inside okay just 20 minutes okay
it's around you all the time we can call
it the biggest frustration in the world
right if you touch it for 20 minutes you
become a diamond angel okay and it's
around you all the time so just do it
what are you waiting for
and it's a big frustration because we
can it's just hard to see someone has to
train you you need very specific
training to see it if you have that
training if you have a good husband in
the kitchen teacher you can do it okay
you can do it anybody can do it
it's not you have to be in the time of
the Buddha you have to have shared head
you have to have a robe your hat new
name has to be Ananda or shariputra it's
not true don't think these are
historical people it's you okay don't
think it's only people in Buddha's time
it's not it's you okay you you have very
clear information how to do it may be
clearer than what Buddha students huh
okay and you have to just do it okay
you can do it everyone in this room can
do it and if you get old and die you
will curse me you will say get a lot
didn't tell us to do it fast do it fast
okay do it fast
pack your bags two days before you go to
them and then relax okay you don't have
much time you know and you will never
get a chance like this okay
don't wait any you should know that
shock you won't get it again easily you
won't get this chance again
use it no okay see emptiness and you
have everything you need
okay in the ACI courses in it you have
everything the DCI manual for number
seven I think it's the most practical
manual for seeing emptiness then any
sutra okay I think so okay all right
then we study dependent origination
right let's talk about that tangent Dawa
to say protea somewhat bother then I
hate this word dependent origination it
it definitely doesn't pass the radar
test if you go in the Mexican restaurant
and say could I have a dependent
origination
they say we have tacos /
we don't have the penetration okay
that kind of some kind of salad or
something okay so uh I tried for many
years to find a better translation
nowadays I kind of like dependence
dependence it's not enough but things
depend on other things D to not date
room say D chumina dates from the
ancient ancient ancient definition of
dependent origination if this happens
Dada happens if this happens that
happens
I can't got it and to be honest in this
homework I called it interdependence but
it's a little too much on the both ways
you see dependent origination doesn't
necessarily mean both ways it it means
it actually but it's not the emphasis so
interdependence is not very precise I
think dependence might be better things
depend on other things
nothing happens from nothing nothing
comes from nothing nothing never okay
okay
and by the way books have been written
about the pen origination the vasa
bandha wrote a book which will be a
thousand pages when we translate it just
on the twelve links okay it's an amazing
subject you can spend ten years on this
subject it's so Gong is translating one
of those books and it will take him
about ten or fifteen years and they are
delightful they are delicious
okay by the way the translation classes
from sedona are online for free I did 72
classes in January and they're free and
if you don't watch them you're dumb dumb
ok they're very fun and confusing ok but
you can learn so much just swimming does
put them on when you go to work ok
you'll understand two or three sentences
but they're amazing those classes are
amazing you're crazy if you don't listen
to them sometimes just listen to them in
the car you know put them on when your
cookie okay no it sinks into your brain
okay it doesn't cost anything okay
brainwash yourself okay all right this
book this commentary by poppin kombucha
is it has some of the best explanations
of these ideas of any book okay this
little book principle teaches it has
some of the best explain it has the best
explanation of dependent origination I
have ever seen and I use it almost every
day okay if you want to know dependent
origination read the reading for this
class class nine okay so I'm gonna go
through three kinds of dependent
origination okay the third ones the
correct one but the first two are super
sexy
okay all right first one belongs to the
first three schools together which is
detailer school sutras school in mind on
this code these three schools have the
same explanation of dependent
origination okay
and they're called functionless group
except for word hundred dollars why they
called functionalist together they're
called functional less schools where
every aroni started I don't know she's
gonna finish
clothes kinda but why are they called
functionalist yeah good so $100 for
their handsome guy the other handsome
guy
yeah like gasoline has a power in it to
drive a car to make a car go fire has a
heat inside functions belong to things
functions exist in things okay so that's
a belief of 75% of Buddhists ok they
think nobody put heat in the fire they
make a joke they say Diamond Mountain
did didn't hire a person to go around
and make all the cactuses thorn sharp
they just are
ok the characters thorn is charm nobody
got hired to sharpen all the cactuses in
diamond mom that's just what the
function lies anything ok so that's why
they're called functionalist ok now
somebody Daniel the here comes Daniels
answer ok if you ask them what dependent
origination they will say yeah all
things depend on causes ok and that's
you know there's a Ingo in in Chinese or
something and when they say dependent
origination you you think oh things
depend on their causes baby depends on
the mom I don't know food depends on
cook you know thousands of examples ok
and that's when you first heard
dependent origination someone taught it
to you
99% they said things come from their
causes ok things come from their causes
and this is dependent origination
where's that dependent origination in
the kitchen yeah the yelling husband
came from the from I planted seeds by
yelling at the kids I create the cause
by yelling at the kids and the result
came out the yelling husband is not in
the independent the yelling husband
depends on yelling at the kids
what's the classical proof word that
something is a cause for a result
what's the classical proof that
yeah good if you start making the cause
the result was done which in in the
kitchen is yeah if you never yell at the
kids the husband will never yell at you
it's impossible okay got it
that's the lowest of the three kinds of
dependent origination on question two on
homework nine what's the group that yeah
those three schools together which are
called the funkiness group because they
believe fire is hot the function of fire
to burn lives inside fire nobody put it
there but really they did you made the
fire hunt
okay got it that's why you can walk on
water okay you can walk on water it's
very famous in Buddhism I had it in a
debate and I screwed up so I never
forgot it it's a discussion of whether
water can be solid so yeah okay number
two first tell me does the dependent
origination of the first three schools
cover everything no there's things that
don't have causes which do exist
okay there are things which don't have
causes which do exist like your husband
yelling at you right I didn't do
anything
result came right no okay give me an
example space okay spit space and
emptiness are two famous examples if you
want to get really fancy yeah the
permanent ending of things like if you
learn the pen and you never go to animal
birth again that has its own dependent
origination
it's a negativity it's a negative okay
all right so this is lower middle way
school all things depend upon their
parts and that's dependent origination
all things depend upon their parts and
that's real dependent origination
because you function those guys you left
out unchanging things cause and effect
only applies to changing things but
there's things in the world that don't
change someone explain to me why space
doesn't change for $50 because I did it
the force base is like ten thousand
times not you were just forget it unless
I ask you okay
yeah if Eric stands up and by the way
I'd like to welcome Eric Ali on his
fiancee
I think the first time he came here I
ran into him on the road I said you need
a ride he said now I'm just out for a
while you know first of all that's weird
why is this guy have time to take a walk
and then he had a bunch of papers in his
hand do you remember and it was all the
information about the affordably and so
I've been coming here for 19 years I've
never been there I never had time and he
he was curious to see the history of
this place and I thought that was so
cool I said no Ali now I believe she got
a good one you know somebody with good
curiosity you know about where you are
you know what happened here and why is
there this place here and you know
anyway I'm I'm glad you're here and I'm
glad you've caught a good fish you also
caught a good fish okay so lower-middle
way things have parts and as gills I
just mentioned if Kelsey gets up and
goes to the kitchen the space she's
occupying will stay there and if she
comes back and sits down again the space
will still be there it doesn't move it
doesn't go away okay that's why it's
unchanging okay does it have parts yeah
front back left and right okay so even
those things have parts if you're
interested more on this subject you can
read venerable Apollo's book she's
trancing a book on emptiness meditations
which is a genre of literature called
Tati say Tati it's just books about
emptiness meditations so we added it to
our translator team she's the emptiness
meditation expert so if you want to go
deeper on this idea ask her for oh it's
online right it's free online all of our
transactions are free online
in fact there's a place where when you
read them you have to make comments like
this is really a dumb translation okay
yeah okay good
is that it all right okay that's where
the video is I Tim never take a video of
me from the bag okay if if number two is
lower middle way what's number three
yeah higher weight higher men away and
it just means that all things depend on
the pictures coming out of your seats
all things depend on the pictures that
come out of your seats where's this
higher dependent origination in the
kitchen yeah when you open the door and
the seat opens and the husband starts
yelling he's originating dependently on
the seeds you planted with your kids
okay cool yeah Steven
yeah you know in DCI we call it this
okay in DCI we call it this you want
explains to me loud
yeah so the this part is correct in the
mind on this core but they say the
husband and the seed live in the
foundation consciousness you are
watching a video in your mind okay
the higher school says the video is so
good it can be outside okay cool good
question and I remember this is one of
the only times I ever interrupted my
scripture teacher gives you two tonight
it's I think I interrupted him once in
12 years or something and that was the
question
that's an interrupt about question it's
one of the best questions you can ask
okay okay so what's the the Tibetan
extender the Sanskrit is practice some
would bother you don't have to worry
about it okay
[Music]
last thing we're actually gonna finish
on time I guess yeah
by the way they told me to leave before
you guys leave so they can hit you up
for a read on boss I support it just
because I have a word in my life okay if
it wasn't for that I don't need it my
house is very very very cheap I live in
the smallest legal house in here okay
here's the question three Buddhism
teaches that no self exists
what's that non-existent itself look
like okay God by chilla modern power
dating lumens in my N word three hundred
dollars last chance to make some money
off me honey I'll set it again gotta
chill America day momentum my author
meaning two hundred one hundred one
hundred holding at 170 fifty thirty
thirty bucks
that's I have to do with him right get
him flustered it's very difficult yeah
okay
Santi damn I said if you don't know
what's not there for good Antonis if you
don't know what's not there forget
emptiness and that's called in Tibetan
gotcha any in the ACI courses as an ACI
teacher you shouldn't use foreign words
that's kind of a deal we have together
okay don't impress people I mean impress
them and then stop using them okay but
you are allowed to use gotcha because
there's nothing like it in English I
like to tell when I teach it to new
people I say it's like gotcha gotcha say
gotcha
yeah gotcha easy definition one sentence
yeah what emptiness is emptier what's
not there in the kitchen what's not
there in the kitchen if you don't know
the gotcha what's not there in the
kitchen if you say your pockets empty so
but what's not in their money okay or a
credit card but especially a credit card
that doesn't work anyway okay so where's
the gotcha in the kitchen yeah the
husband who dis I like to say the
husband who decided to yell are you okay
yeah I didn't do anything husband come
on Luca say it a little bit more is that
what you say with your husband oh I
didn't do anything
how do you know me okay when you teach
it you have to it's a good time to wake
up the students half of the half of them
are I didn't I think there are like what
what happened
he's a classroom yeah the husband who
yelled at you when you didn't do
anything is the gotcha and his absence
from the kitchen is emptiness okay cool
okay so now you know the answer to the
question self nature self thing which
comes from its own side okay a husband
who can yell at you without you making
any seeds before by yelling at your kids
is Atman in good ancient Sanskrit self
the self but it means the thing which is
itself okay sometimes I like to call
emptiness ready nowadays I'm translating
many pages in there I like to use things
are not themselves things are not
themselves okay that's no self nature no
self nature doesn't pass the waiter test
but if you go into the restaurant and
you say I don't have to pay you know
guys that's why and you say because
money is not money that's really that's
cooking it is coursing whether you will
not get the police call you I don't know
okay
things are not themselves okay things
are not the husband the husband is
yelling is not the husband is feeling
without seats okay without your seats
not nothing in the universities that I
think in my life you know if I'm
teaching you the reason I'm teaching
this is we have a teacher training for
the first time in 27 years and I'm very
happy about it and I heard very good
things about you guys and I believe
we're gonna start a revolution so
welcome to the revolution
all these new ACI teachers I'm very
excited about it I really I really
really like it but I in my own heart my
own presentation has changed a lot in 27
years you know it took 27 years to come
to the kitchen you know and and again I
ask you as a se Aiye teacher keeping in
the kitchen if you can't explain every
idea in the 18 courses in the kitchen
you're not a good teacher
okay because people even if they come to
your class cuz you you're handsome or
you're beautiful like Peter or Maria
they won't stay unless you bring it to
the kitchen okay they won't stay in your
class if you don't teach them to use it
at home okay you're in their workplace
okay so when you teach emptiness you
know I beg you teach it in the kitchen
teach it from the kitchen then later
teach the model philosophy and say the
hair stuff in the kitchen here's a mind
only in the kitchen
here's Sutras in the kitchen okay keep
comparing it to the kitchen or you
failed
you're wasting their time okay if you
teach emptiness well the first night
they hear about emptiness the third
principle path their marriage should
start to improve that night if you're a
good ACI teacher and you teach them
emptiness principle Path number three
correctly from the point of view of the
kitchen first and then go give them big
words okay
their marriage should start to improve
that night
same night okay cool
thank you I'm gonna go you have to stay
stay a long time huh oh sorry Connie
rerun the scene and a empathy son gation
do mater who are you
and hold on she loves your show and I'm
gonna try my luck Yong Tae Yong
he Tim lined up that video made a okay
gay why the kale walk-on turn on your
shirts all talk she turn on yes
corny talk okay just when you teach when
you teach have fun okay this is Taiwan
last month and please please please
don't please please please don't be too
serious have some fun and your students
will love it and they will love you for
your whole life okay here we go
ready go